Brian Griner, Ph.D.

(609) 418-1644 / briangriner@protonmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/briangriner/briangriner.github.io

Summary

Commercial analytics professional and data scientist with work experience in commercial pharma, CRO, CSO and healthcare consulting the the areas of marketing science, econometric modeling, multivariate statistics, data science, machine learning, and deep learning. Technical skills include programing languages R, Python 3 (using scikit-learn and keras for TensorFlow and Theanos; NLTK, Gensim, Word2Vec, GloVe), SAS, SQL, Apache Spark (SparkR and PySpark). Server platforms include Unix, FreeBSD, Enterprise/Amazon Linux, Ubuntu. Cloud platforms include aws, GCP, and MapR

Experience

Data Science & Learning Systems, LLC

Princeton, NJ

Founder

June 2017-Present
Consulting on design and implementation of machine learning systems for marketing and sales support

- Consulting on design and implementation of machine learning systems for marketing and sales support
 Development of machine and deep learning pipelines for workflow automation and quality control:
 - o Gradient Boosting Machines and Multilayer Perceptrons for regression and classification
 - Long Short-Term Networks for time-series forecasting and document summarization
 - Natural Language Processing for topic modeling and document classification
 - Word Embedding Convolutional Network for sentiment analysis
 - Encoder-Decoder Recurrent Network for image captioning
 - Impact: use of standardized ML and DL pipeline frameworks can reduce development costs by 50% or more

Boeringer Ingelheim Pharmaceuticals

Ridgefield, CT

Senior Associate Director, Data Strategy & Innovation

Jan 2016 - May 2017

- Primary care-Specialist Rx influencer model
 - Model identified Rx multiplier effects from target Specialists to Primary Care physicians of 1.7-1.9 in large primary care market with 23 m patents
 - Impact: 70-90% potential cost reduction with the same reach by reallocation of promotional activities from primary care physicians to specialists
- Influencer Rx Potential Score from patient referrals and prescribing behavior
 - Target list augmentation for personal, virtual and and non-personal promotions
 - Impact: New capability for targeting new Rx influencers for personal and non-personal promotion
- Sales rep approvedmail promotion-response model
 - Predicted incremental Rx associated with rep approved email channel
 - Identified physician email responder segments
 - Identified key drivers/barriers of physician email click-through rates
 - Impact: New capability to target physician email responders to increase click through rates from rep approved emails
- Rep outbound call center promotion-response model
 - Predicted the impact of call center intervention in slowing the loss of sales associated with exclusion from a large payer formulary
 - Impact: able to the measure profitability of the rep outbound call center campaign
- Use case development of MapR data-lake
 - Developed Epics and User Stories with senior leadership to drive design of data-lake
 - Developed use case for text analytics of inbound call center data used by Medical Affairs
 - Identification and documentation of data-lake inputs with Data Governance
 - Impact: increase in productivity and quality of deliverables through use of data-lake by inhouse analytics teams
- User testing of Adobe Workbench platform for digital analytics

Quintiles, Inc.Cambridge, MAChief Methodologist, Integrated Health Services, Advisory2014-2015

- Directly supported sales of over \$1m in analytics projects for commercial division
 - Dynamic line-of-therapy market share/health outcomes model using EMR and Rx data as part of a special project for CEO
 - Impact: integrated commercial offering creates potential for up and cross selling clinical services
 - Created Bayesian network simulator on cloud-based platform (aws) using claims data to
 - Predict demand to inform client decision on label extension
 - Identified physician prescribing behavior not consistent with product labeling

- Impact: opportunity for medical education to physicians on dosing and titration consistent with product labeling
- Market share rep and support service quality model to identify key quality metrics for client sales force to inform training programs
 - Impact: Ability for client to prioritize rep training to achieve Rx impact
- Member of Global Publication Policy team

Chief Methodologist, Market Intelligence, Consulting

2012-2014

- Directly supported sales of \$2m + in analytics projects for consulting division
- Value based pricing simulator for new oncology and HCV products
 - Impact: used to support pricing decision for major pharma client
- Linked value driver simulator for forecasting demand, price, and market access level on pre-term labor product in development
 - Impact: used to support a Go-No Go decision on phase III clinical trials by large pharma client
- PRO-based patient engagement and health outcomes structural equation model for large COPD franchise
 - Impact: used to drive a patient engagement program by a large pharma client

Kantar Health New York, NY

Senior Methodologist, Advanced Methods

2010-2012

- Directly supported sales of \$2m + in analytics projects for market research division
 - Dynamic order-of-entry market share simulator to support forecasting business
 - Automation of code to create advanced conjoint-choice experimental designs
 - Training of junior analytics staff on new advanced methods
 - Impact: Directly supported sales of over \$2 m in analytics projects for research division

BioVid, Corp. Princeton, NJ

Executive Director, Strategic Analytics

2007-2010

- Patient case-based linked stakeholder demand simulator for forecasting
- Message bundling simulator for message positioning
- Latent class segmentation-predictive scoring model for predicting segment membership on a client target list
 - Impact: new products developed contributed over \$4m in sales

Strategic Business Research

Horsham, PA

Vice President, Strategic Consulting & Advanced Analytics

2005-2007

- New proposal templates and pitch decks for quantitative business increased win rate by 50%
- Integrated message bundling-benefits laddering model for product-patient-message positioning
 - Leverage qualitative data to drive quantitative insights
 - Impact: increased market presence through presentation at national industry conference

Target Rx Horsham, PA

Director, Client Solutions & New Product Development

2002-2005

- Supported \$1m in sales for start up division targeting sales to specialty pharma and biotech
 - Member of ProSigma product team supporting new product development
 - Developed ProSigma Message to leverage Detail Performance Score used as benchmarks in ProSigma detail and Detail Performance Monitor offerings
 - Impact: augmented revenue potential of the ProSigma product line by creating up sell opportunities for the larger Detail Performance Monitor offering

Griner Consulting, Ltd.

Founder

Rocky Hill, NJ

2001-2002

Created a Lifetime Value Model for a major automotive client

- o Identified key drivers of Lifetime Value
- o Predicted Life Time Value score for new customers on vehicle registration list
- Presented model insights to senior management
- Impact: Provided major auto manufacturer with strategic insights to manage new customer relationships to increase future revenue streams from repeat sales

Ipsos-Reid, Corp.

New York, NY

Vice President, CRM & Data Mining Systems

2000-2001

 Led new division to create systems combining survey research with secondary data sources for customer relationship management

- Designed automated customer satisfaction-early warning system for large retail client's inbound call center
 - Won Ipsos 'New Solutions' global company competition
 - Impact: Call center CRM system helped client prevent defection of most important accounts due to customer service issues

Lightspeed Research

Murray Hill, NJ

1999-2000

Vice President, Research

- Member of leadership team that started Lightspeed GMI consumer panel http://www.lightspeedgmi.com now part of WPP Group
- Impact: methodological design ensured projectable results from consumer panel research

Opinion Research Corp International

Princeton, NJ

Manager, Telemarketing Modeling

1998-1999

- Dynamic machine batch learning model for targeting telemarketing campaigns
 - Impact: dynamic targeting model increased sales per hour on scored retail banking lists resulting in 50% longer campaign duration and incremental revenue of \$3-4m

Blockbuster Entertainment Group

Dallas, TX 1997-1998

Senior Market Segmentation Analyst

Optimal new video release allocation model

- Designed field experiment to optimize distribution of new videos across stores
- Impact: optimal new release allocation predicted increase of \$5m in incremental profit

SDR, Inc. Atlanta, GA

Senior Research Associate

1996-1997

- Designed complex discrete choice and conjoint studies for pharmaceutical, petroleum, and consumer package goods industries
 - Impact: use of optimal experimental design principles from dissertation research provided enhanced capabilities for complex conjoint and discrete choice projects

Education University of Pittsburgh

Pittsburgh, PA

PhD, Public Policy Research & Analysis with honors

1998

- Dissertation "A Valuation of Water Quality Enhancements in the Lower Allegheny Watershed using Discrete Choice and Conjoint Analysis" Advisors: Stephen Farber, Wagner Kamakura, Hector Correa, William Dunn
- Award: 1997-98 Doctoral Program Award for Academic Excellence Conducive to the Advancement of Knowledge in Public and International Affairs in the Graduate School of Public and International Affairs

MPA, Public Administration

1992

• Thesis: An Evaluation of Alternative Methods for Forecasting Regional Industry Employment in the Pittsburgh Region. Advisors: Sabina Dietrick, Vijah Singh, Ralph Bangs

West Chester University

West Chester, PA

B.A. Speech Communications/minor Political Science with honors

1990

Research

Publications & Conference Papers

https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Brian Griner/publications